Guide to the Fortunoff Video Archive for Holocaust Testimonies Collection of Related Documents and Ephemera
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Fortunoff Video Archive for Holocaust Testimonies collection of related documents and ephemera
1899-2008
MS 1913
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.38
(11 boxes)
The collection includes original and facsimile documents, photographs, manuscripts, clippings and other items related to individuals who have given testimony to the Fortunoff Video Archive.
Fortunoff Video Archive for Holocaust Testimonies
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Material donated to the Fortunoff Video Archive for Holocaust Testimonies. Transferred to Manuscripts and Archives, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Use of these materials will require registration at Yale's Manuscripts and Archives. As is the case with other materials from the Fortunoff Video Archive, permission to view these materials is not the same a permission to publish or cite from these materials. Any citation of individual items from this collection must use the "cite as" field in the corresponding catalog record (see Associated Materials). Only the first letter of the survivor's surname is used to protect that person's anonymity.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Associated Materials
Each survivor that contributed materials to this collection has a corresponding video testimony in the Fortunoff Video Archive for Holocaust Testimonies. Each testimony is represented in Orbis, Yale's online public access catalog, with a bibliographic record associated with the testimonies HVT# (Holocaust Video Testimony) -- the unique identifier used to locate testimonies in the Fortunoff Video Archive. These records contain a brief summary of the tesitmony and several Library of Congress subject headings, both topical and geographic. To locate the corresponding bibliographic record in Orbis, you will need to conduct a keyword search for "hvt-#" (including the quotation marks), i.e. "hvt 30".
Scope and Contents
The collection includes original and facsimile documents, photographs, manuscripts, clippings and other items related to individuals who have given testimony to the Fortunoff Video Archive.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in ascending order by HVT #, which is the unique identifier employed by the Fortunoff Video Archive for Holocaust Testimonies.
Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945)
- Leon W., Undated; HVT-2 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains personal narrative book chapters entitled "Baluty," "Leaving the Ghetto," "Liberation," "Living in the Ghetto," "Our Neighborhood," "Pinchow," "The Lodz Ghetto," and "Wajnberg Bakery."
- Frank S., Circa 1980; HVT-30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Contains narrative concerning Kristallnacht.
- Selma E., 1943; HVT-42 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Contains translation of diary; identification cards from United States Holocaust Memorial Museum of Selma E.'s relatives; and clippings.
- Hela S., 1983; HVT-68 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Contains photographs of Hela S.'s family.
- Walter S., 1945; HVT-146 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Contains photographs of Walter S. and survivors of Buchenwald; newspaper clippings; photocopy of identification card and certification; letter of verification by H.E. Wortsmith of the 6th A. Div C.I.C.; speech by Walter S.; and a copy of an interview of Walter S. by Donald M. Douglas followed by a copy of a testimony by Walter S.
- Daniel F., 2010; HVT-153 and HVT-987 (Box 1, Folder 4a)
  Contains a newspaper article about Daniel F.'s liberation from Dachau and his reuniting with Rainbow Division liberator Morris Eisenstein.
- Karl S., 2003; HVT-173 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Contains a copy of leaflet included for a conference that has a short biography of Karl S; and a copy of a drawing showing where Karl S. hid for eighteen months as a child in southeast Poland.
- Baruch G., 1994; HVT-295 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  Contains a letter from Baruch G. to Dana L. Kline on his reflections on the 50th anniversary of the end of WWII, and a bound copy of Baruch G.'s memoir covering his life from 1939-1995.
- Nadia P., 1985; HVT-534 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Contains letters from Van Jeffreys Frankel, James Young, John Van Doren, Susan Broockman, Eve Tahmincioglu, Peter Sherm, and family members to Nadia P.; a letter to Joanne Rudof; poetry by Hilan Dov Warshaw; and narratives by Michael P.
- Marion L., 2003; HVT-543 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Contains a program for a memorial celebration of Ilse Johanna Hess.
- Lilli K., 1982; HVT-545 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Contains published booklet of six lectures on the Holocaust by Lilli K., Emory University Center for Research in Social Change.
- Eric H., 1947; HVT-574 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Contains an English and German copy of an affidavit given in the Office of the Liberated Jews in Munich describing treatment by the Boryslaw Police, and a newspaper clipping.
- Nicholas P., 1985; HVT-575 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Contains a poem by Nicholas P., and a narrative about the liberation.
- Sydney (Zoltan) S., Circa 1940-1942; HVT-580 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Contains a letter to Hariette Friedlander; a narrative and autobiography by Sydney S.; copies of maps; photocopies of various identifications and certifications; photocopy of identification booklet cover for Joseph Friedman; brief biography of E. Herschkovits; photocopied photographs of Jews in Hungarian labor camps; 1942 hospital notice forbidding entry of diseased individuals; and a photocopy of a photograph of a mass grave in Bergen-Belsen camp on the day of liberation.
- Abraham S., 1985; HVT-615 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Contains newspaper clipping with quotes from Abraham S. about the Fortunoff Archives.
- Paul G., 1938; HVT-621 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Contains two copies of physician order issued by the Organization of Physicians of Vienna.
- Frieda G., 1981; HVT-627 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Contains narrative by Frieda G.
- William K., 1945; HVT-635 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Contains letter written in 1945 by William K. to his parents; poetry by William K.; and two narratives by William K.
- Esther A., 1981; HVT-639 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Contains transcript of Esther A.'s testimony given at the Yad Vashem at the gathering of Holocaust survivors in Jerusalem, June 14-18, 1981.
- William F., 1986; HVT-693 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Contains article about William F. written by the Federation of Jewish Philanthropies.
- Meta N., 1946; HVT-696 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Contains clippings; a personal narrative; a newspaper article on Meta N.'s passing; and a copy of a play based on some of Meta N.'s Holocaust experiences.
- Marion P., 1947; HVT-754 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Contains newspaper clippings.
- Coen R., 1945-1949, 1996; HVT-759 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
  Contains photo of Coen R.; a newspaper aritcle about Coen R.; and Coen R.'s war report written from 1945 to 1949, in Amsterdam, for the War Documentation Center of the Netherlands. (523 pages).
- Michael J., 1944; HVT-763 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Contains photos; identity card copies; copy of a letter verifying work status; and a copy of address papers.
- Margrit R., 1990; HVT-773 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Contains a personal narrative regarding Margrit R.'s Holocaust experiences in Theresienstadt.
- Julia P., 1986; HVT-774 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Contains an announcement of Julia P.'s photography exhibit at Quinnipiac College in Connecticut; contains newspaper clippings about the exhibit; and a memo suggesting that Joanne Rudof visit the exhibit.
- David P., 1986; HVT-783 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Contains two memoirs by David P. about his experiences in the Holocaust.
- Mary M., 1986; HVT-792 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Contains three personal narratives about Mary M.'s experiences during the Holocaust; two self-relfective works about her memories/experiences; and a letter to Mrs. Schiff regarding "Operation Bowl of Soup" in the Warsaw Ghetto.
- Pierre T., 1987; HVT-836 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Contains presentation speech given by Pierre T. to the United States Holocaust Memorial Council regarding non-Jews who were persecuted by the Nazis.
- Solomon S., 1997; HVT-850 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Contains narrative about Solomon S.'s experiences during the Holocaust as well as family history, including photographs, historical birth record, and a family tree.
- Gaston S., 1992; HVT-851 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Contains a family history of Gaston S.'s family including a "current residence" list of living family members and relevant narrative information for those family members who were affected by the Holocaust.
- Jacob W., 1987; HVT-901 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Contains two songs sung in concentration camps (one copy of "Das Judenlied" and two copies of "In Thuringer Land").
- Konrad B., 1942-1947; HVT-928 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Contains copies of a "Lucie to the Rescue" French undergound resistance movement comic; school identification card; correspondence from 1945-1947; a police order dated September 17, 1942; an "Acte De Disparition" for Fanny Ettinger dated 1947; and an interview intake form.
- Henry O., 1944; HVT-942 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Contains English and German copies of a letter to Reichsfuehrer-SS H. Himmler requesting the transfer of the scientific section in Concentration Camp Plaszow to Concentration Camp Flossenbrueck to continue the work of the Institute for the German Eastwork.
  - Additional material for HVT-942, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Contains copies of published reviews of Henry O.'s book, I Shall Live, copies of German documents related to Henry O.'s experiences and English translations of them, copy of a Ravensbrück registry with the names of Henry O. and his brothers; and comments on his book from educators.
- Fred O., 2003; HVT-943 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Contains an article from the Washingtonian entitled "When Dad Needed Me," by Fred O.'s son, J.B., about his father's life experiences during the Holocaust.
- Manek F., 1945; HVT-952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Contains Russian language copies of letters and identification cards from October and November of 1945.
- Margarete L., 1983 April; HVT-958 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  Contains a biographical essay by Margarete L.
- Frances B., Undated; HVT-959 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  Contains Yiddish poetry by Frances B. about her experiences, including some English translations.
- Murray B., 1968 and undated; HVT-960 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  Contains English memoir by Murray B. and a copy of an article from the September 7, 1968 Yiddish Forward.
- Ilse L., 1987; HVT-967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Contains German language biography of Ilse L.
- Leokadis W., 1988; HVT-981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Contains a personal narrative/academic paper by Leokadis W. on the Holocaust.
- Stanley O., 1946; HVT-990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Contains a short biography of Stanley O.; documentation of his time in the Polish military; copies of his false identification papers; and newspaper clippings on Stanley O.
- Luna K., 1988; HVT-1095 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Contains newspaper clipping on Luna K.
- Wolf Z., 1988; HVT-1096 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Contains newspaper clipping on Wolf Z.
- Marion P. and Anton P., 1947 April 2; HVT-1097, HVT-1098, and HVT-1099 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  Contains one issue of Windshejmer Lager-Biuletin, a newspaper of Windsheimer Displaced Persons Camp (issue number 10), printed in Yiddish in Roman alphabet.
- Claire H., 1942; HVT-1186 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Contains police permits for members of Claire H.'s family; statement that Claire H.'s family received information and declaration of property sheets; memos and instructions of the Secret Police regarding the evacuation of Jewish residents; and a brief registry.
- Edmund M., 1988; HVT-1219 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Contains newspaper clippings about Edmund M.
- Isabella L., Undated; HVT-1270 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  Contains articles and reviews of book and play based on book, Fragments of Isabella.
- Janet R., 1987; HVT-1279 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Contains a narrative by Janet R. (nee Zenia Esienberg), taken from the Ostrog Book, about her family; and a Yiddish writ, published in 1954 in Argentina, by a survivor.
- Lilly W., 1948-1949; HVT-1283 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Contains various correspondence from World ORT Union; identifcation papers for Imre Weiser's employment at the ORT Central Headquarters in Germany; driving certificate for Imre Weiser from the Preparatory Commission for the International Refugee Organization; a recommendation letter for Imre Weiser; Notification of Personnel Action for Imre Weiser; Certificate of Authority for Displaced Persons for Imre Weiser; a copy of the June 26, 1949 Hersey Herald; and a document in Hebrew.
- Felix F., 1988; HVT-1287 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Contains Felix F.'s resume, and a copy of the Paparim Dance Ensemble Newsletter which features a piece on Felix F.
- Frieda Z., 1989; HVT-1291 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Contains a memoir by Freida Z., titled "Searching for Shadows," about her trip to Warsaw, Birkenau, and Auschwitz.
- Sarah W., 1985; HVT-1293 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Contains a portion of the narrative, published as a series by Emunah Women of America, Committee on the Holocaust, by Sarah W. about her experiences in Luxembourg, Marseilles, and Switzerland during the time of Nazi Germany.
- John R., 1985; HVT-1295 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Contains a State of New York Legislative Resolution honoring John R., and an opinion piece, written by John R. for The Generation After, on the Holocaust.
- Isabella L. and Philip K., Undated; HVT-1319 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Ilse S., 1988; HVT-1380 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Contains newspaper clippings; advertisements for presentations and courses on the Holocaust given by Ilse S.; two poems and two short writs by Ilse S.; an autobiography; photographs of Ilse S.; a map of Judischer Friedhof indicating the locations of family members' graves; correspondence from Congress member Barbara Kennelly, Elie Weiesel of the United States Holocaust Memorial Council, Senator Lowell Weicker, and Sam Goldberger; and a copy of the Congressional Record for October 18, 1988 second session of the 100th Congress in which a poem by Ilse S, in response to President Reagan's visit to Bitburg Cemetery, is published.
- Etta W., 1939; HVT-1482 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  Contains photos of Etta W. and her father, and a photocopy of the passport used for her travels to Budapest.
- Henny S., 1945; HVT-1498 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  Contains a letter from Henny S. to family members after the liberation, and a memoir about her experiences during the Holocaust.
- Herman B., 1945, 1990; HVT-1583 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  Contains copies of 1990 correspondence from Herman B. with Museum of Jewish Heritage/A Living Memorial to the Holocaust regarding documents and art donated to the Leo Baeck Institute and an exhibit of those articles as well as a listing of photographs and documents considered for donation to the Museum of Jewish Heritage. Also contains copy of an article in the New York Daily News, September 18, 1945 about Herman B.
- Abraham U., 1990; HVT-1635 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  Contains a newspaper clipping on Abraham U.'s experiences during the Holocaust and his return visit to Poland.
- Aranka S., 1982; HVT-1648 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  Contains an interview of Aranka S. on writing books for children about the Holocaust; newpaper clipping on Aranka S.'s books; two copies of publisher advertisements for her books; a copy of a January 18, 1992 issue of Newsweek which includes a review of her book Upon the Head of the Goat; and a copy of a Fall 1990 Kerlan Collection newsletter that includes an announcement of a public lecture by Aranka S.
- Eva H., 1990; HVT-1713 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  Contains a collective memoir written by Eva H., her mother and her father.
- Fred F., 1945; HVT-1717 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  Contains a letter from Fred F. to his mother dated May 19, 1945.
- Chiel M., 1990; HVT-1730 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  Contains a personal narrative regarding Chiel M.'s Holocaust experiences in Poland.
- Bruno G., 1991; HVT-1764 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  Contains handwritten biographical notes.
- Dan G., 1997; HVT-1846 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  Contains a narrative by Dan G. about the liberation in Seehaupt; photocopied photos of the Hauptbaustelle Flugzeugwerk Mettenheim of Nazi Germany; a photocopied photo of the liberation of Muhldorf; and current group photos of the survivors of the Muhldorf/Seeshaupt death train.
- Eugene R., 1944; HVT-1878 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  Contains diary and drawings of Eugene R.'s experiences at Barth Concentration Camp.
- Claudine K., 1945; HVT-1971 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  Contains letters sent by Armand (Abraham) Kahan from train headed to Auschwitz; letter written after the liberation of Auschwitz; letter sent from Katowice; letter sent from Kursk; and a telegram and transport ticket.
- Ola S., 2003 April 21; HVT-2035 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  Contains a one page article from Newsweek written by Ola S.'s daughter.
- Sarah M., 1992; HVT-2257 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  Contains five personal narratives written by Sarah M. regarding her experiences in Poland, Paris, and Switzerland during the war of 1939-1944.
- John W., 1991; HVT-2264 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  Contains an advertisement made by Atlantic Union College of a speaking engagement by John W., and newspaper clippings on John W. and his Dutch-Paris underground organization.
- John M., 1946; HVT-2271 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  Contains John M.'s honorable discharge documents, and photocopies of pages from The Last Offensive, a volume of the series United States Army in World War II, marked to document/validate John M.'s Army experience during WWII.
- Abraham B., 1992; HVT-2277 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  Contains a personal narrative by Abraham B.
- Matthew T., 1995; HVT-2349 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  Contains a letter and drawing of Kulkin's Courtyard that was sent to Ernest Ratowitz about the Ratowiczes and Polish of that area; correspondence between Matthew T. and Joanne Rudof; three versions of a personal narrative by Matthew T. that include photographs and drawings; a photo of artwork by Matthew T.; and a thank you card from the Emanuel Synagogue of West Hartford, Connecticut, featuring artwork by Matthew T. entitled "Shabbat and the Tree of Life" and a booklet explaining the details of the artwork.
- Madeleine M., 1990 and undated; HVT-2354 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  Contains copies of articles about Madeleine M.; a map; and The Ravensbrück Prayer.
- Werner H., Undated; HVT-2408 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  Contains a photocopy of a New York Times article about the Jewish ghetto in Shanghai during World War II.
- Frank S., 1976; HVT-2413 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  Contains newspaper clippings about Frank S. and his artwork.
- Helen S., 1945; HVT-2502 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  Contains a narrative by Helen S.'s husband about his experiences in the Oswiecim (Auschwitz) Camp.
- Celina H., 1933; HVT-2521 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  Contains a copy of the Museum of Jewish Heritage Video History Project Questionnaire; photographs of family members; and a memoir of Celina H.'s wartime experiences as a child.
- Thomas H., 1993; HVT-2522 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  Contains a bound copy of Thomas H.'s memoir, Then, Death Was Decreed, covering his life from 1929 to 1945.
- Anita S., 1899; HVT-2556 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Contains letter to Anita S.'s cousin from her father in Oranienburg Camp.
- Phillipe P., 1940; HVT-2586 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Contains intake interview sheet for video testimony; correspondence from Joanne Rufof; and copies of wartime letters written by Phillipe P.'s father.
- Erika M., 1994; HVT-2617 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Contains newspaper story about Erika M., her husband's, and her family's experiences in Slovakia during World War II.
- Lisa O., 1994; HVT-2622 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Contains a resume for Lisa O., a German citizen, detailing her guest speaking and authorship experience on the Holocaust. Resume also includes a chronology of Lisa O.'s experiences in Nazi Germany.
- Amelia B., After 1986; HVT-2740 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  Contains an unpublished manuscript of Amelia B.'s life.
- Kurt L., 1988; HVT-2753 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Contains a newspaper clipping on Kurt L., and an autobiography.
- Irena D., 1948; HVT-2756 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Contains an autobiography of Irena D.'s experiences from 1939 to 1945.
- Henry K., 1990; HVT-2826 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Contains a letter in Polish and a translated copy sent from the National Museum in Auschwitz to Joesph Kahn regarding documentation on Kokotek Pesla and her imprisonment in Concentration Camp Oswiecim-Brzezinka (Auschwitz-Birkenau).
- Herbert L., HVT-2830
  - "About the Holocaust, Christian Guilt and Related Issues", 1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    A document/opinion piece written by Herbert L.
  - "Auschwitz Lies" [commercially produced], 1990; 1 (Box 9)
    A survivor documentary filmed in Auschwitz by Loebel Prod. Inc.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository.
- Fiszel S., 1988; HVT-2971 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Contains a Spanish booklet entitled "Testimonio" which details Fiszel S.'s experiences during the Holocaust.
- Pearl P., 1985; HVT-3027 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Contains correspondence sent from the American Gathering of Jewish Holocaust Survivors to Eva Kor; a page from a register book at Auschwitz; a press release from CANDLES (Children of Auschwitz Nazi's Deadly Lab Experiments Survivors); a memorial pledge by CANDLES; and a list of the surviving Auschwitz/Mengele Twins used in the experiments.
- Joseph T., 1990; HVT-3128 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Contains a piece written for B'nai B'rith by Joseph T. about his trip back to Poland and his memories of the Holocaust.
- Idek R., 1939; HVT-3130 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  Contains a German letter.
- Esther F., 1985; HVY-3383; 1 (Box 10)
  Tape of a survivor personal narrative entitled "Esther's Life Story."
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
- Judita K., 1988; HVT-3754 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  Contains a special issue of Borba, a Serbian newspaper, listing the names of child victims of the Holocaust, and personal narratives of Judita K.'s experiences during the Holocaust.
- Jack T., Undated; HVT-3766; 1 (Box 11)
  Military footage showing Jack T. as a little boy.
- Italo S., 1941; HVT-3769 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  Contains photocopied photographs of classmates and faculty from a Jewish high school in Milan, Italy.
- John F., 1998; HVT-3797 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  Contains memoir written by John F.'s sister, Helga Harrison, about her experiences in Vienna, her prewar emigration to England, and her current correspondence with individuals she had known during that time.
- Shmuel Z., 1996; HVT-3804 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  Contains two bound copies of Shmuel Z.'s memoir, translated from Hebrew to English, covering his life from 1928 to 1996.
- Deitrich G., 1988; HVT-4085 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  Contains two papers written by Deitrich G. about the Holocaust.
- Moses D., 1932-1950; HVT-4098 (Box 4, Folder 17)